Hi there everyone. Welcome to the very
first day of the Kaggle Generative AI
Intensive Course, a 5-day course being
delivered virtually so that you can
learn everything there is to know about
Generative AI and how to use it in your
AI applications. Today we have a bunch
of really great guest speakers that are
going to be talking all about
foundational models as well as prompt
engineering. Um and even though we had a
couple of snags on the live stream
earlier this morning, um we've packaged
up to uh the video all together um such
that you'll be able to have a really
really nice experience walking through
both an overview of the course, a Q&A,
um a brief overview of some of our code
labs, and then also finally our pop quiz
towards the end of this series. Um so
this uh this 5-day course on Generative
AI with Google um by Kaggle will give
you daily assignments in the form of
white papers and podcasts that you'll be
assets to listen to. Um these assets
explain the what and how of how all of
the Generative AI uh Generative AI
models, uh tools like vector databases,
um agents, how all of these different
uh different techniques and uh different
techniques and tools work together. Um
and the accompanying Colab notebooks are
intended to show you how to use it um
both our Generative AI APIs as well as
other assets um like open-source tools
that that you might use with them. Um
we've also got a great Discord channel
for you to discuss and
uh and to to kind of brainstorm ideas,
um and to also get direct uh the direct
ability to engage in Q&A with our guest
speakers. Um we're hoping that you'll
take this moment to to kind of deep dive
into all of the content that we've
created and to learn some of the
fundamental important uh, and kind of
top-of-mind concepts around tech with
generative models. Um, so, as I
mentioned, this is a 5-day program,
um, uh, over the course of November 11th
through November 15th. Today is our very
first day, um, and it will be discussing
all about foundational models and prompt
engineering. So, with that, and without
further ado, let's get started with our
Q&A for this very first day.
Greetings and welcome, everyone. We're
excited to have you today for our first
day in our generative AI intensive
course sponsored by Kaggle and the
Gemini team. Um, we have a lot to cover
today, so I'm going to get right into
it. Um, everything from answering the
great questions that you've been asking
on Discord, um, to having some exciting
guest speakers kind of talk about what
they've been working on, also walking
through some collabs and some demos, uh,
and then finally a pop quiz. Um, so,
really excited to have you here today.
We've been really energized by the great
questions that you've been adding on
Discord, um, and I'm excited to see
just, uh, just how much everyone is is
caring about learning more, um, learning
more about large language models,
multimodal models, uh, and generative AI
at large. Um, my name is Paige. I'll be
your host for this week, um, and I am
joined by many of my colleagues here
today, um, and hopefully, uh, hopefully
we'll be doing some introductions a
little bit later. Um, so, this 5-day
generative AI intensive course has a
combination of daily assignments, um,
the Discord threads that we've been, uh,
that we've been discussing, as well as
these live Q&A sessions. Um, we'll have
them 5 days a week from November 11th to
November 15th, um, and it covers
everything from foundational models and
prompt engineering to embeddings and
vector databases, AI agents,
domain-specific models, um, and even ML
ops for how you can maintain these model
systems over time. Today is all about
foundational models and prompt
engineering. And so we have many many
folks on the call who have been doing
this as their day job for the past many
years
and who are
kind of experts to help answer your
questions as you cover all of the great
readings in the in the chat threads and
the discussions
each day. So with that, I am going to
get into it in the interest of time to
make sure that we have we have ample
space to discuss all of your questions.
This Q&A segment will be a continuation
of all of the things that you've been
seeing on Discord
and I want to make sure to thank our
wonderful generative AI Discord
moderators Pulong Cause, Mark, Eric,
Irwin, Miles, and many of the other
folks that have been kind of diving in
and helping. Make sure to emoji thank
them
and also also text thank them. I know
that they've been busy and working in
every single time zone. The The sun
never sleeps on on generative AI at
Google.
Um
So with that,
day number one, our expert host panel
includes Logan Kilpatrick,
who's the product lead for AI Studio,
Lee Boonstra,
Alexy Severin,
Majid Amin Baraxen,
Daniel Mankowitz, Chuck and Anand.
And I'm excited to have everyone here
today.
As an example,
we have folks that have worked on
reinforcement learning with human
feedback, people who have been working
on people who have been working on the
Gemini app model inference, making it
performant and efficient,
technical directors from the office of
our CTO,
and even more. And with that, I'm going
to go ahead
uh and uh and start with our first
question um to Logan. Good to see you,
Logan. How are you doing?
I'm doing awesome. I'm excited to both
hear the questions from folks, but also
hear some of the questions for some of
the other uh
panelists.
Excellent. Very cool. And the ML
developer team has been shipping so much
just recently. It feels like every day I
log on to to LinkedIn or to Twitter um
or X or or whatever it's called now. It
seems like there have been new product
releases. Um, tell me which features
you're most excited about um and which
uh which have already launched or about
to launch.
Yeah, that's a great question. I think
the two that are top of mind right now
um about 2 weeks ago we landed grounding
with Google Search, which is really
exciting. So, I think this will surely
be a topic of conversation over the next
5 days, but LLMs and hallucination and
grounding and
grounding with Google Search is is a way
to sort of tap into the the search index
that Google has and bring some of that
information to ground answers rather
ground questions that that users of LLMs
have. So, super super interesting.
There's Yeah, if you just Google Search
grounding with Google uh you'll you'll
find some some of the links across the
developer side, the enterprise side.
Um
So, excited about that. Happy to talk
more about it. The other thing is
Friday we landed
uh OpenAI compatibility, which I'm super
excited. So, for developers who are
already using the OpenAI SDKs and
libraries, um you can now try out the
Gemini models using those SDKs and
libraries by only changing like three
lines of code or something like that.
So, um excited to to sort of reduce the
friction for developers who are excited
about using Gemini and
um yeah, hopefully we'll we'll hear a
bunch of great feedback about that
launch as well.
Excellent. I personally have been really
really jazzed for uh for the Open AI API
compatibility. Um it's been really,
really straightforward to convert
notebooks that might have been
preferring the Open AI APIs to just
using Gemini um and to be able to
compare and contrast between the two. Um
so those are those are definitely two
exciting things that have come out um
and I encourage everyone to take a look
at the at the Open AI compatibility and
then also the search grounding features
um within AI Studio. I think it's
especially cool that you can use search
grounding with even some of our smaller
models uh like Gemini 1.5 Flash and
Gemini 1.5 Flash 8B.
Um I've been loving both of those for my
projects, especially things um requiring
uh
um you know, code execution or our super
fast inference. Um uh tell me tell me a
little bit about those two Flash series
of models um uh and how you can do so
much so quickly um with a very small
cost footprint.
Yeah, so we we landed um after a bunch
of work internally, we landed the Flash
AP model, which is the smallest uh sort
of Gemini hosted model that that exists.
Um 8 billion parameter model and really
pushes sort of the envelope of, you
know, compute intelligence per dollar. I
think we've seen a bunch of those
tweets, Paige you and I have have been
ones putting those out, but it's like 2
3 cents per million tokens. If you're
using cached tokens, it's 1 cent per
million tokens. So, just like an
absolute
an absolute crazy amount of intelligence
that you can get for
um for a couple of cents. And I I think
the the sort of interesting thread of
why those small models are interesting
to me is because a lot of the, you know,
frontier use cases of AI are actually
bounded by
uh by cost and token cost. So, like
there's a lot of things like the
developers actually inherently have a
disincentive to build because it's like
you you are paying the more AI
the more AI you build into something the
more you pay. Um and I think Flash API
is like a great example of sort of
pushing the frontier of trying to like
remove that barrier so that developers
can actually just build the things that
they're excited about um and not need to
sort of worry about, you know, the
incremental amount of cost that they
take on.
Yeah.
Amazing. Um and then one last question
and then we're going to we're going to
bring in some more folks to to discuss
uh especially the production
applications of of generative AI.
Um you know, DeepMind's multimodal
models uh I'm thinking particularly of
Imagine and VEO for video generation,
Lyria for music generation. They unlock
some really interesting new applications
especially when coupled with the Gemini
models. Um what has been your favorite
application for for these kind of um
multimodal output scenarios? Um and uh
and
how do you think about coupling those
with the Gemini APIs?
Yeah, that's a really good question.
I I think the
it is so hard to create
um or
rather I think
text as sort of like an output mechanism
for models, I think like, you know,
developers have found the interesting
things to do with text. Like, you know,
you build chat apps, you sort of process
data, you do a bunch of stuff. It does
feel like we're actually still pretty
early in this like what are the real
actual production use cases of
multimodal output creation
um both in image, video, and others.
Like, I
been as much ubiquitous access to those
models and thus like developers haven't
had enough time to really build
interesting things. Um
I think that the the The that I'm
personally excited about is is actually
like comparing or or rather bringing
text to life using those things. Like I
think there's just like a lot of text in
the world and humans and in a lot of
cases are inherently visual.
And I think if it's possible and we sort
of saw this with NotebookLM actually as
an example like if you can take a bunch
of written content and bring it to life
in audio form, it actually makes the
experience like 10x better in some
context and I can imagine, you know, the
sort of
I'm not on the NotebookLM team, so this
isn't actually a product vision for
them, but
you know, you bring to life sort of the
the huge corpus of text documents you
have in the form of a video instead of
just like an audio conversation. I think
that's like a that's a crazy future
world to to live in and I'm I think it
is going to be models like imagine in
video that actually enable that mission
to come to fruition. So, it's going to
be it's going to be exciting. And I see
your lights just turned off. This is
folks who uh
don't know the Google offices, the
lights turn off all the time, so it's a
it's a normal occurrence.
Yes. And the And I I love that use case
as well about how you can sort of bring
life to text documents or even to to
things like GitHub code bases through
video, through audio, through images.
I think my favorite use case so far has
been doing book trailers.
So, so taking in taking in a PDF book,
automatically, you know, segmenting it
into into different into different
prompts,
and then creating a short video to
describe the book.
I I love it. Um and and would love to
see love would see love to see more of
that thing.
So, thank you so much. This is This has
been wonderful.
I I'm going to pull up pull up our next
question,
which is all about reinforcement
learning with human feedback.
And I'm going to bring bring on stage
Alexi. Alexi, you're
uh me if I'm wrong, you're our lead or
RLHF for the for the Gemini app, is that
correct?
Correct.
Excellent. Thank you. And uh I'm really
uh I'm really curious to learn more
about how uh the Gemini app is using
RLHF to help improve its responses.
Um uh how do how does that process work?
How do you uh sort of use user feedback
um to to improve improve the models over
time or to improve your app experiences
over time?
Yeah, um so I mean it's a very big
topic. Uh so maybe it makes sense uh to
say a few words uh on a high level how
the LLMs are fine-tuned.
So, like the de facto recipe today for
post-training uh state-of-the-art LLMs
is uh to do it in two steps.
SFT and RLHF. SFT is supervised
fine-tuning
where we use demonstration data.
And I mean typically to get good
results, uh this data needs to be of
extremely high quality, and it's most
often
uh produced by human experts, so it's
quite expensive to get.
RLHF is uh a powerful technique uh for
aligning models to human preferences.
Um
yeah, think of like making responses
safer, more helpful, or factually
correct.
And uh it's a bit more complicated than
SFT, um but in brief, uh we use uh a
collection of input prompts to generate
responses from the model that we're
trying to fine-tune. And then you use
another model called reward model to
penalize responses
uh that are bad and reward uh the good
ones.
And this reward model can be uh
fine-tuned on different types of
preference data. So, typically it's
human preference data. This is what
uh RLHF stands for, like human uh uh
reinforcement learning with human
feedback.
Um and this data can be collected from
human expert raters, just like um, SFT
data, or it can also come from um,
uh, user feedback. So, people like users
interacting with uh, Gemini uh, chatbot
on on the desktop or their mobiles.
So, the thumbs up, thumbs down, uh,
interactions that we that we uh, do with
the models actually actually lead to
better performance over time. Is that
what you're saying?
Yeah, it helps us to produce models that
are perceived as more helpful uh, to our
users. So, this is kind of one of the
primary mechanisms to align uh, our
models uh, to human preferences.
Amazing. That's that's really exciting
to hear. And I know folks have been
learning all about RLHF and all about
improving models with things like human
feedback um, through the through the
course of their readings.
Um, the next the next question is
um, uh,
from from one of our folks at Google.
So, I've been wondering um, since large
language models learn from massive
sources of data, do large language
models simply interpolate within their
training data, or can they go beyond to
make new discoveries? Um, and Amin, how
about how about you answer that? I I
think uh, and then also uh, welcome
back. I believe I believe you used to
work at Google DeepMind, and now you
started your own company. Is that
correct?
Uh, uh, no, actually I I I I I I used to
work at DeepMind, but now I'm I'm I'm
work for a new company called
Quadrature.
Uh, so, yeah.
I I switch industry, actually.
Nice.
And Quadrature, is that in the finance
industry and quantitative quantitative
research?
Yeah, with the quantitative research.
These days you can basically apply AI in
in any application, and finance has been
also very very interesting application.
Very very cool. So, so tell me uh, tell
me about the
models making new discoveries. Have you
have you
that is the case or are they just
next token predictors?
Yeah, yeah, I mean that's
like a philosophical and interesting
question.
But
I believe the answer to this question is
is yes, the models can definitely go
beyond their training data. And the
technique that will let them do that is
a very old search basically. So
the first example
that we saw that was the work
called fun search that we did in deep
minds
end of like 23. And in fun search we
basically used an LLM to search in the
space of Python programming language for
let's say a very hard problem like an NP
problem. NP-hard problem. And the way it
worked was that we basically paired an a
large language model with an efficient
let's say evaluator that would provide
feedback on how good each solution is.
And then with an iterative algorithm it
managed to discover new solutions for
some open problems in computer science
and mathematics. So the core idea was
that the LLM would basically propose
let's say solution solutions like a
piece of code for a for a particular
problem. And then the evaluator would
give some scores on on how good that
solution is. And then there was an
evolutionary algorithm that would select
the best solutions that the LLM
discovered so far. It would presented to
the LLM and it would basically ask it to
make it better. So in some ways it was
doing best shot prompting like an
automatic way of prompting the LLM. We
would just show it good solutions. We
ask them to make better. The LLM comes
up with something new. We would show it
again and and ask it to make it better
and and this sort of process is repeated
about 100,000 of times. And then the
code that we it starts with is something
like a return zero, and it would like
evolve into something very interesting
and complicated that would actually
result in some new, let's say, solutions
for open problems. And it because this
basically solutions has never discovered
by humans before, it kind of shows that
the LM discovered something new that
wasn't in its training data. And this
concept has been like
basically studied a lot like in the
history of AI and recent examples.
Recently, it has become very popular in
the modern LLMs, and it's referred to
by, for example, test time compute or
inference scaling and other
terminologies. And and the way it works
is that like
you can basically
when you ask a question for the LLM,
you allow the LLM to think, and the LLM
would basically generate multiple
scenarios and generate like chains of
reasonings. And then, it has a mechanism
to understand that, okay, which one is
more likely, and then it would just
iteratively repeat this process, and by
simulating different possibilities, it
basically search at inference time. And
with by searching at inference, it it
can manage to like basically discover
something new because it can bootstrap
its own knowledge.
Very cool.
And and that makes me that makes me
think that we've only just begun to tap
into the kinds of things that that large
language models will be able to
accomplish or to achieve.
Exactly.
Really, really excited to to see what
the next five years hold.
Exactly. Like I I I I think like Rich
Sutton puts it the best way we have like
in the bitter lesson that like we have
two techniques that basically scale
infinitely. The first one is like
learning, which sort of we cracked by
like, you know, large amount of data and
and just like with the
like the first, let's say, generations
of models we saw. And then the next
technique is search, and I think we are
at the moment where where people are are
starting to scale search and throwing
computer inference time and that's going
to unlock a whole lot of new
capabilities especially for like
reasoning capabilities and that's going
to be very exciting.
Excellent.
Um thank you so much. I I think I think
this also leads is a great lead to our
next question
which was from our Discord app.
Um
and I think this is for Majid. Majid
you're our inference lead for the Gemini
app.
Yeah. Excellent and
so so this question is is really
is really all about can larger language
models be used to train smaller ones.
Can we take some of this knowledge that
that might have been obtained from a
larger model and use it to improve
smaller models.
Things that
kind of like the models that we embed
within many of the product surfaces at
Google. What are your thoughts about
that?
Yeah absolutely. Yeah absolutely we can
and that's a very good question.
This technique is called distillation.
It's a very popular inference
optimization technique
and the main idea is as you said Paige
you would take the knowledge from a very
large model that might be too expensive
to serve but has very good quality and
then you would distill that knowledge
into a smaller model
that can retain a good amount of that
knowledge and quality of the big model
but is at a at a size that you can
serve. So yeah like I said it's a
technique called distillation lots of
active research and practice in in
distillation.
There are multiple types that you can
distill knowledge from our larger model
to a smaller model.
One of them is called data distillation
where you use the larger model to
generate a lot of synthetic training
data for the smaller model and then you
just train the small model on that.
Another way we can do this is more fine
grained where we try to align the token
distribution for the smaller LLM to be
closer to the larger model. And that's
what we would call knowledge
distillation.
And we talk about those types in the
white paper that we're publishing with
this with this class as well. And the
third type that I would mention is
called on policy distillation where kind
of going back to your discussion with
Alexey on RLHF,
we would be able to use the same
reinforcement learning framework, but in
this case we would use the teacher
model, which is the larger model, to
effectively score output from the
smaller model and use those scores to
train and align the smaller model to to
the larger model.
So yeah, distillation has multiple
types. They're all used in practice
based on the use case and based on what
we need.
And actually I think in tomorrow's class
one of those cases will be presented as
well. I think
one of the authors for the Gecko paper,
which uses LLMs to
improve to produce much better embedding
models using LLMs. So you would use the
LLM to essentially produce query pass
the query
queries for for passages and then you
would train the embedding models on that
and you would get a much much better
performance. I think it was something
like 7x better for those embedding
models of the same size using
distillation.
And I think Jin Hyuk Lee, who's the
author on that paper, will be present in
the vectors and embedding classes
tomorrow.
Very cool. I think I think what you just
discussed will also be very helpful for
the folks in our first pop quiz, which
should be coming up towards the end of
the hour. So I hope everybody was paying
attention all about the the great ways
that you can use distillation to improve
smaller models
and mechanisms mechanisms to improve to
improve models at large. Thank you so
much. Yep. And next next question. I
believe this is for you Anand.
What are some approaches to evaluating
large models? You know, we've we've got
we've got these models that have been
created, some larger versions, some
smaller
versions. How do you pick which one that
you should use for a given task?
Good question, Paige. And yes,
thanks for the community for asking
this. And just a heads-up, we'll be
covering evaluation of large language
models in more detail on day five. We
even have somebody from DeepMind who'll
be who'll be presenting their research
on it.
Yeah, so diving straight into questions.
So, this evaluating large language
models isn't an easy task because it
depends on the task you're evaluating
and what you mean by evaluation. There
is, of course, classical natural
language metrics like blue rouge scores
which you can use. And this is one of
the ways you can do it where you have
reference like a golden truth ground
truth then you can see what the LLM
generated and then you can compare the
the generated response with the human
curated ground truth and you can see how
to what extent it matches the ground
truth response. Now, that is classical
way to do it. However,
given the complexity of tasks LLMs are
used and you might not always have such
a ground truth and even when you do on
certain tasks,
you can for example summarization,
there is multiple ways to write a
summary and all of them might be valid
but the ground truth would be just one
such instance. So, it would not be a
valid way to evaluate such cases as
well. So, what we can also do is use LLM
as alterators where you where you kind
of have an LLM evaluate an LLM
and and evaluate how good the response
of the
generated by the
the model was and you can do this in in
a point-wise fashion, in a pair-wise
fashion where you can just say, "Okay,
here's the response. Here's my prompt.
How well on a score of one to five do I
does this response score and why is it
why is that the case or in a pairwise
fashion you compare two responses and
say okay
tell me for this prompt which one is the
better response and it says okay
response the left one is better because
whatever reasoning and we actually have
that available so you can use that right
away and our Vertex suite of through
Vertex AI generative AI evaluation
service you can try
LLM base auto rater evaluation as well
as computational metrics like Rouge and
Bleu which use a reference point you can
try that out today.
Absolutely and I've also seen some
pretty impressive open source libraries
doing auto rating and evaluations as
well
have been really delighted with prompt
food which also has the Gemini API
support
and and some of the other some of the
other offerings so great to know that
there are Vertex AI options as well as
open source libraries to go about doing
these evaluations whether they're human
rated or auto evaluated.
Very cool.
Excellent. Next question from red 365.
Can someone please explain why for the
first chain of thought prompt it's also
explaining step by step instead of
answering that directly. Lee I see you
nodding do you want to go ahead and take
this question?
Yeah yeah I can talk a little bit about
that because I had similar yeah examples
in the in the white paper that I wrote.
And um
So first of all for the folks on the
call like chain of thoughts chain of
thoughts of thought prompting
and that's a prompting technique where
you yeah you try to let the LLM generate
intermediate steps.
And
typically you can do that by providing
examples on how to reason. And then you
don't take the example as what's in the
collab, you try to come up with another
example that which has similar reasoning
techniques.
And yeah, then you see if it will then
showcase the steps. Now, this particular
question and and thank you everyone for
yeah, participating in the collab.
I saw some people saying like, "Hey."
Cuz in the question you had to first
type in an example where we did do not
use cot prompting and then the
afterwards we will show an example and
an example where we use chain of thought
prompting so you could see the
difference. But the problem was that
some people so as already saw the the
the intermediate steps in the first
first example, while it shouldn't.
It's very difficult nowadays with models
that get so good, you know, our our
models are so good like we cannot
showcase these flaws anymore.
But uh
you might be able to reproduce it by
either like often maybe
just resubmitting the the question.
It might help also just to change the
the top K, top P
or temperature so you get more variance
in the in the outputs. And I saw also in
the in the chat some folks saying that
switching to the older Gemini models
will showcase how you can
showcase the flaw and then later you can
fix it with chain of thoughts. So,
that's cool stuff.
Very cool. I I love I love kind of the
detailed description of of chain of
thought in and of itself and then also
how you can see it expressed as model
outputs. This is very very cool.
And personally I I found especially for
things like
like coding tasks, chain of thought
prompting or or asking the model to
explain its reasoning has been very very
powerful and has usually led to
significantly better results.
Yeah.
So, this is this is very cool.
The next question uh from Woosung Kyum
is um, is something like enum mode
um, a a fine-tuned model designed to
return enum values?
Um, and Daniel, uh it's great to see
you, by the way. Uh welcome back. Uh uh
for folks on the call, Daniel and I used
to work together at DeepMind.
Um,
and now uh now I believe you have
started your own company uh
uh or you're still in stealth mode for
your company, so I won't I won't give
spoilers. Um, but it's great to have
you. Would you like to answer this
question?
Yeah, sure. Yeah, nice to see you as
well, Paige. And uh yeah, thanks for
having having me. Um, yeah, and I and I
think that uh
in in terms of enum mode, I mean, it it
it very much depends on on what you're
trying to do. So, if you're fine-tuning
your model
um, and you want it to output enums,
this depends a lot on how you structure
your data. So, for example, if you have
three different enum values that you'd
like to output, um you would structure
your inputs as the question or task that
you want to provide to your LLM, and
then the output would be one of the enum
values, whichever one is most relevant
to uh the question or task um that you
asked the LLM to provide a output on.
Um, and uh so, you can fine-tune LLMs
like that and generate your prepare your
data sets with these inputs as being the
task or questions and the outputs being
the enums.
Um, and also,
you know, LLMs are also sometimes very
good out of the box in dealing with
enums. So, you can also say to an LLM
something like, "These are the different
types of classifications that you can
choose or enums that you can choose.
Um, choose the appropriate one for the
question that we're asking." So,
suggestion would be to also try it
zero-shot, and if not, you can create
these fine-tuned data sets.
Um, and I think there was a question
about uh related to notebook uh LLM that
was uh
along these lines, Paige.
Um yes, uh I believe the the question
that you were referring to was um from
the screen of us,
um which is all about uh all about
notebook LLM, how it was built, how it
was uh how it was created. I really
really loved experimenting with it as
well as the illuminate kind of automatic
podcast generator for any arbitrary data
types.
Um the uh I For notebook LLM,
interestingly enough, um and this was
shared by Josh Woodward at a recent
event, um it's not using a fine-tuned
version of Gemini. Um it's just using
Gemini 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash um with uh
with the addition of some special
techniques um and some secret sauce,
especially around retrieval and around
uh kind of careful prompting and design
of the system. Um so so notebook LLM is
not relying on a dedicated fine-tuned
example of Gemini. It's just using the
same Gemini 1.5 models that folks are
experimenting with for your assignments.
Um so that's a a great way to get
inspired um in that, you know, the tools
that you're building with are the same
tools that folks are using to enrich AI
applications at Google, um which is
which is very cool.
Um
Beautiful.
Um just just want to point out uh uh we
noticed there's some freezes sometimes
happening from the community on the uh
on the live stream
um and uh we'll also be we also got
feedback that you'd like us to cover
some of the course like white paper
overviews. We'll be covering that later
in the call as well.
And uh let us all speak loud so
everybody can hear.
Excellent. And with that, I am going to
go ahead uh and thank our presenters for
uh thank our presenters again for
kind of answering all of the community
questions. Make sure to to reach out to
connect with them on on LinkedIn to
learn more about their work or to follow
follow the papers that they've been
writing. And
virtual virtual round of applause. I
know that Riverside does not does not
support emoji reactions, but thank you
all so much for your time. This has been
this has been really wonderful
and a great way to to learn more about
all of the the great content for day one
of our generative AI intensive course.
So thank you for being here.
With that, I'm going to go ahead and
move to our next session
which is all about code labs and demos
for many of the great many of the great
code examples that are included in the
course. I'm going to stop sharing and
then Anant, I believe you are you have
some notebooks that you want to walk
through. Is that correct?
Yes, that is correct. And let me
um
I believe that everybody on the live
stream I believe the freezing might be
happening due to the live chat. So try
try turning off the live chat. That
might help.
Cool. Let me share my
screen.
All right. So hi everyone.
I would Today I'll be going through the
collab with you for this session. And
before I do that, however,
for those of you who are joining the
live stream for the first time without
going through the podcast or the white
paper, let me just take a step back and
give you a quick overview of what the
first day was about. So you might have
received two white papers and
corresponding notebook LM podcasts. And
they talk about basically the first
white paper about foundational models
talks walks you through okay, what are
LLMs? Um how are they the fundamental
component of how they are what makes
them. So, the transformer architecture
which inspired this whole revolution
with LLMs.
And then it goes into how do you train
LLMs? Um how it like fine-tuning
techniques uh through fine-tuning as
well as reinforcement learning using
human feedback and other things. Then we
briefly talk about um the parameters
which are important for LLMs
uh and prompt engineering like coding
type parameters which we'll all also be
covering shortly in this collab. So,
things like temperature, um uh top P,
top K, etc. The way the LLM constructs
the response. And uh and then we talk
about prompt engineering briefly. And
then we have a whole white paper uh
written by my colleague who um
uh which is on the call earlier which
talks about prompt engineering
techniques. This is the second white
paper that you might have received.
And then in the first white paper that
we then go ahead and talk about uh uh
how to accelerate uh inference of um of
LLMs which uh my colleague Matched here
just talked about through techniques
like quantization, distillation,
uh uh and um
speculative decoding as well as others.
And then we talk about, okay, how can
Now that you've learned how LLMs are
built, tuned, trained, uh
well, uh accelerated during inference
time as well as
uh how you can utilize them through
prompt engineering, then we talk about
few applications in various fields of
LLMs, how you can utilize them. So,
that's a nutshell um of what your day
one curriculum was about. Of course uh
and um this collab here kind of tries to
walk you through how you can utilize
that. That was the how and this is the
how you can
like how you can put this to use. And
that's what we are going to see right
now.
So, uh my colleague Mark Mark McDonald
was who had created this
uh
uh uh
he's not here in the call today, but
like to give a shout-out to him as well.
And yeah, let's get started. So, on the
Discord
we saw a lot of questions around uh
well, phone verification for internet
access. So, hope you've gotten that
done. That's important and you've
received that in your instructions as
well, but feel free to let us know in
case you have any more questions. And
you might have already seen how to add
Kaggle secrets, which is important to
the Gemini API. When you get the Gemini
API key, you can add that as a Kaggle
secret and then programmatically
retrieve it in the Colab in order to
utilize our APIs. This is important, so
those of you who haven't started the
Colab yet, I hope you've gone ahead and
done this. And then in the beginning
part of the Colab we'll be installing
the SDK, the Gemini AI SDK from AI
Studio. And then we'll be retrieving our
API key through Kaggle secrets in order
to
utilize our Gemini API.
And then we'll be going ahead and
going ahead and
running our first prompt where we use
our Gemini API to just do a single-turn
prompting where we just give a prompt in
and response out. In this case, I always
love it when people can simplify things
for me, so explain AI to me like I'm a
kid. I love this response on Gemini.
I've used our Gemini 1.5 Flash model,
which is
as Paige host discussed earlier that
this is one of the fast fastest models
out there. And yeah, and not only can
you generate response, you can also
format them to make it look nice, right?
And then we the second part of the Colab
is the the subsequent part of the Colab,
we go beyond single-turn interaction and
we kind of see how you can make a
conversational interface with Gemini, a
chat interface.
So you will see here that we send a chat
message to Gemini telling our name, my
name is whatever, and then we ask some
the model responds. It's a response and
then we send another message asking
completely different question and later
on we are querying the model and say,
"Do you remember what my name is?" So
because in this chat interface of Gemini
it keeps a memory, keeps history
internally keeps record of what was
discussed earlier and what its response
was. So it remembers the name correctly
and so this is how you can utilize in
conversational applications, utilize
Gemini in conversational applications
and can be very useful while
implementing LLMs in in production.
Moving on. So
since
LLM the world of LLMs are is moving
quite fast and there'll be like we have
a lot of models coming out and you can
also you might have also trained your
own models or tuned your own models. So
this is how this section talks about how
you can kind of list the models that you
have you have at your disposal and you
can see how you can list them, the
various kinds of models and you can also
get more information about a certain
particular model. For instance, this we
used the Gemini 1.5 Flash the 001
version, the first version of Gemini 1.5
Flash. It has an input token limit and
the context window of 1 million, output
of
around 8,000 and the default values you
can see here as well for
for generating a response. Now talking
about generating a response, for those
of you who haven't read the white paper
yet, just let me give you
a high-level overview. So LLMs work by
generating tokens at each like step by
step. So given the input prompt, it will
look at the input prompt and generate
the next most likely token and each of
those tokens are selected from all the
possible tokens it could generate that
it was trained on, but each one of them
have an associated probability score
given the past sequence which was
generated. So, uh and uh it the system
works by sampling by seeing, okay, uh
looking at the probability scores of
each token at each step and choosing a
token based on those probability scores.
So,
the generation step, there's a lot you
can do to influence the output response,
and that's what we're going to briefly
be looking at here today, but please uh
look into the white paper and the
podcast for more details of how it
works. One parameter is
Yep.
Yep. And then would it be possible to
zoom in a little bit? Uh
to zoom in a little bit on the code.
This is great. I love uh I love seeing
um uh I love seeing kind of the ways
that you can interact with the models
and then also kind of inspect and and
see which models are available uh are
available to use. Um the uh I also
frequently like to do uh if I if I'm not
sure which version of flash or version
of pro is the latest, you can do
gemini-1.5-flash-latest,
uh and it and it ends up grabbing just
the the most recent version. Um so, this
is
Exactly.
Yep. Thank you for
Yep.
Zooming in literally as well as
conceptually. Thanks for that.
Uh and yes, thanks Paige for pointing
that out. And yeah, so once you figured
out which model you'd like to use, um
it's there's a lot you can do at
generation time. One of the parameters
is output length. You can kind of cap
how big or how large your output, the
number of tokens your it is generated by
the response of or present in the
response of the LLM. And uh just
something to keep in mind is you can cap
it. You can say, okay, I would only want
200 token I only want my response to be
200 tokens maximum. It could be lesser.
Um but it does not uh
stylistically change it does not
stylistically force the LM to fit its
response meaningfully within that
restraint. So that what that means maybe
it's more obvious with an example. Let's
say you ask the LM to make a 1000 word
essay. Those of you who have been in
Collab you might have seen this example.
You ask it a 1000 word essay and that's
much more than 200 tokens. So it's not
going to magically reduce this compress
the essay into 200 tokens. So you can
see here it stops mid-sentence.
And that's the thing. So it can reduce
and it can reduce the cost because
you're built that you if you use a paid
version you can you're built by the
amount of tokens you generate as well
one of the factors and you can reduce
the cost and you can kind of force your
LM to limit the output length but you
cannot mean it doesn't make the response
meaningful always. So you have to keep
that in mind.
And you might want to do some prompt
engineering and and change the prompt if
you want to actually generate meaningful
short responses. So like write a short
poem and this would fit within 200
tokens for sure.
Now moving on we discussed earlier how
LM generates how LM generates its
response by
taking sampling probabilistically at
each step by step the tokens based on
how likely the token is at how likely
all the tokens are at each step.
Now one of the things that can influence
the probability and change the quality
of the response not just the length is
temperature. Think of temperature as um
as a way to influence the probabilities
and lower temperature means the
token with the most
tokens with higher probabilities get
even higher probabilities of being
selected and the lower ones get even
lower and
a higher temperature means more or less
all of the
the gap between the best tokens and the
worst tokens are
is narrowed. So basically what that
means is a lower temperature ensures
that or increases the probability that
you will get
kind of similar output even if you run
the LLM repeatedly and a higher
temperature gives a bit more diversity
or creativity and randomness to the
output. Let's look at that with an
example. Let's say we prompt the LLM to
pick a random color.
We ask the random color and answer in a
single word. But as you see here with a
higher temperature value of 2.0, the
colors are different in we are we loop
through it three times
and the colors are multiple times and
the colors are different each time. But
if we have temperature fixed at zero,
then the color is purple every time. So
it's the same. So the the variability is
reduced when you keep the temperature
low.
Talking about temperature, that was on
increasing the probabilities. But what
about across all tokens, right? And what
about selecting the limiting the amount
of tokens we select from not just
modifying the probabilities but limiting
and filtering kind of the top
well-performing tokens
and then selecting from within them.
That's exactly what top K and top P does
and the kind of top K and top P in
interest of time I won't go into detail,
but they basically limit the the kind of
the search space at each step from which
the tokens are selected. You can use top
K and top P parameters in conjunction
with temperature. And this is
this is something you can
play around with to see if it matches
what you would like to see.
Now, briefly covering prompt prompting
the various prompt techniques which you
also see in the in the second half of
the code lab and we have sent a white
paper around prompt engineering as well.
So if you'd like to dive deep, go have a
look at the white paper or at least
listen to the podcast.
One of the most basic techniques is how
people know prompting is zero-shot where
you basically give a LLM an instruction.
Say you want it to classify movie
reviews into three buckets, positive,
neutral, and negative. You give the
review and you ask for the sentiment.
Notice here, you're just giving it an
instruction and you're giving your
input, but you're not giving it more
directions or examples or even explain
what positive, neutral, and negative
means for you.
And it will work in some cases, but in
in other cases it might not. That's good
to keep in mind. And also remember that
you're asking the LLM to generate
positive, neutral, or negative as a free
text field, but you might want to
restrict that to like make sure that the
output that comes out is definitely one
of positive, neutral, and negative and
you don't have to um it doesn't generate
anything else in addition to that.
So, this is where you can use our enum
mode, where you can especially in
problems which are very well structured
such as classification problems where
you want the output to be restricted to
what you a certain format or certain set
of words. Uh this can be very useful
where we use the same example, but this
time we have limited the output space to
exactly positive, neutral, and negative.
You see here that here it was positive
with stars around it.
And here you do not have that. You have
it what we told it to
uh output.
Now, we talked about earlier around
giving an instruction and just asking
like asking the LLM to generate an
answer, but we can go beyond that. We
can give an example or even multiple
examples of input and output to the LLM
and it helps it understand by example.
Uh and that helps improve performance in
certain use cases. You would see an
example here.
And then
and then
and you see here that giving a few
examples of uh
what the response should look like helps
it
reason
and generate better responses.
Now, uh can also we can control the
structure to a more granular extent of
LLMs, and this is what you see in this
part of the collab in JSON mode, where
you can
ask the LLM to output well-formed JSON
structure, and this can be very useful,
especially when used for um coding and
programmatical uh purposes when you want
a well-formed data structure in a
downstream task.
And there was a question around chain of
thought, moving on to more prompt
engineering techniques like that. So, uh
chain of thought, as the colleague
answered earlier, is a technique which
uh
instead of just asking an LLM to give
you an answer, it uh it asks it it it
basically um elicits a reasoning
process. You ask the LLM to reason about
it, and maybe even give examples about
the reasoning steps, and that helps
improve performance on certain tasks
which benefit from this reasoning uh
reasoning um intermediary steps. For
example, here we are um
talking about when I was 40 years old,
my partner was two times my age. Now I'm
20, how old is my partner? If we ask the
LLM to return the answer immediately,
now you see here it gives you the
incorrect answer
because we asked it to give the answer
immediately, while the the model could
have benefited from the reasoning steps,
intermediary reasoning steps.
So, that's where now we try and ask the
model to think step by step, uh and it
uh it managed to come up um with the
correct answer, and it does so by
explain kind of does a calculation and
uses that logic intermediary reasoning
steps to arrive at the answer. Uh you
can go beyond this, you can even give it
examples, so few-shot chain of thought,
where you kind of give it examples, and
then write the reasoning of how uh the
output was arrived at, and it can make
it even more powerful for certain tasks.
Talking about reasoning, we have another
powerful technique which was discussed
in the white paper, and we see that
here, reason and act. So, developed by
Google, so React framework was is one
where you can
we don't just ask the LLM with a single
response to give us an answer. We have
the LLM in a multi-step workflow where
the LLM does searching. It kind of it it
thinks about
we have it interleaved thought, action,
and observation steps. So, we give it a
prompt, we ask it to think about it, and
then take an action, maybe call some
tools, and techni- uh tools like maybe
even APIs and SDKs, which we'll be going
into more detail uh in the agents day
three um session. And uh and then see
the response it got from say a database,
reason about the response, then take a
further action, and so on and so forth.
Um uh this is a very powerful technique
which can uh when implemented uh
properly can be very powerful in in in
in applications which require multi-step
multi-step workflows.
And uh yes, uh going on to our last
section. So, here we saw how you can use
LLMs from uh
also text generation LLMs uh like Gemini
uh with for um for generating code. So,
we see here that it can be used for
generate code directly, but you can also
see that uh you can use it for you can
have the LLM not only write code, but
also execute code by using some of our
tools. For example, um
uh code execution tool where it figures
out, okay, which to answer a certain
prompt, you might need to do some
calculations or execute some code. Uh
and it does it can do so, it can write
that code and execute it behind the
scenes, and give you the the response as
well.
And and I I I just want to be being
mindful of time. It looks like we're at
time, uh and it also sounds like there
have been some AV issues
um with folks on the live stream. Um so
so just want to uh just want to say
thank you everybody to attending. Um we
will uh make sure to post
we will make sure to post a video
without any of the live stream kind of
technical difficulties on YouTube that
so folks can watch and can see
and we'll also be sharing the pop quiz
immediately afterwards. Thank you so
much everybody for dialing in
and to all of our to all of our great
questions and answers.
Thank you Anant for presenting for
presenting the notebooks. We look
forward to seeing you tomorrow.
Really appreciate you. Really appreciate
your time.
Thank you and and see you see you
tomorrow.
Thank you.
All right, everyone. Now it's time to
put what you've learned to the test.
We're going to have our first pop quiz
for day one
all about foundational models and prompt
engineering. So get out your pens, your
pencils, your paper or just something to
quickly jot down your answers.
The next six questions will test your
learning comprehension both for the
white papers that were part of the
homework reading
as well as everything that you've heard
in the Q&A today and our code labs.
So with that I'm going to go ahead and
get started with this first question.
Which Gemini configuration setting
controls the degree of randomness in the
selection of the next predicted token?
We would discussed this a little bit in
the code lab but hopefully you were
paying attention. So I'm going to give
you a couple of seconds to think about
your answer
and to show the multiple choice
options. We have temperature which is
value A, top K which is value B, top P
which is value C
and output token count which is value D.
Which one of these
which Gemini configuration setting
controls the degree of randomness in the
selection of the next predicted token?
Hopefully, you're getting your final
answer.
Um, and I am going to count down to show
the answer in 5
Hopefully, y'all all picked temperature,
and temperature is that sort of knob
that you can dial that controls the
randomness in the selection of the next
predicted token for your model.
Beautiful. I hope you got it right. And
if not, make sure to go back and refer
to the reading as well as the code labs
to help build
to help build that knowledge base.
Um, so question number two. Which of the
following is not a technique used to
accelerate inference in large language
models?
Some options that we have. We have
quantization for value A, distillation
for value B, flash attention for value
C, and fine-tuning for value D. This was
covered a little bit in in some of the
Q&A,
as well as the white paper readings.
Which of the following is not a
technique used to accelerate inference
in large language models?
I'm going to count down 5
Hopefully, everybody picked fine-tuning.
Fine-tuning is not a technique used to
accelerate inference in large language
models.
Next question. Which of the following is
a unique characteristic of the Gemini
family of large language models?
Something that Gemini possesses that
other large language models do not.
Um, we're going to show the answers. So,
number one, Gemini models were the first
to introduce the concept of unsupervised
pre-training.
Value B, Gemini models can support
multimodal inputs.
Value C, Gemini models are decoder-only.
Or value D, Gemini models can support a
context window of up to 2 million
tokens. Which of the following is a
unique characteristic of the Gemini
model family?
I'm going to start counting down.
Remember, this is something that Gemini
can do that other models cannot.
Um, counting down, five,
four,
three,
two,
one.
Hopefully, everybody picked D. Gemini
does have a 2 million token context
window for Gemini 1.5 Pro, which is
significantly longer than other models
available today on the market. Um, so if
you missed this, make sure to go back
and refer um to our white papers as well
as to experiment with the Gemini models
in AI Studio.
Question number four, how does
reinforcement learning from human
feedback improve large language models?
And remember that section of the Q&A um
with our our great uh
our great guest speakers from the Gemini
app.
So, value A, by training the map
by training the model on a massive data
set of unlabeled text. Value B, by using
a reward model to incentivize the
generation of human preferred responses.
Value C, by reducing the number of
parameters in the model for faster
inference. Or value D, by converting the
model into a recurrent neural network or
an RNN for improved performance. How
does RLHF improve large language models?
And so, think about what your answer
will be. Remember also the white papers
and the great Q&A conversation that we
had a little bit earlier.
Five,
four,
three,
two,
one. Hopefully everybody picked B, which
is uh
reinforcement learning with human
feedback uses a reward model to
incentivize the generation of human
preferred responses. So, as you're
getting feedback from your users, all of
that is going back into the model to
help improve it over time.
Question number five, we're almost to
the end. Which technique enhances an
LLM's reasoning abilities by prompting
it to produce intermediate reasoning
steps leading to more accurate answers.
Um this you should remember from your
code lab as well as from the from the
reading.
So, value A is zero-shot prompting,
value B step-back prompting, value C
self-consistent prompting, or value D
chain-of-thought prompting. Which one
enhances an LLM's reasoning abilities by
producing intermediate reasoning steps?
And I count down. Five,
four,
three,
two,
one.
D, chain-of-thought prompting. And
hopefully everybody will go back and
experiment with this. I found it to be
really really useful for um especially
for uh kind of complex tasks or things
that would require the model to write
code. Um chain-of-thought prompting
usually usually helps quite a bit for
this.
And final question, and I will say this
is a tough one. Um you'll have to have
been reading very very carefully the
white papers and all of your homework
assignments. What is the minimum GPU
memory needed for inference on a
3-billion parameter model using standard
float precision?
Is it value A 3 GB, value B 6 GB, value
C 12 GB, or value D, 24 gigabytes. Um,
and this is related to your reading. Um,
I will say that if you have hardware
targets that are a little bit different,
some of these values might also be a
little bit different. Um, and it might
depend on how you've int uh int
quantized your out uh your model. So, if
it's int four versus int eight. Um, but
I'm going to start counting down. Five.
Four.
Three.
Two.
One.
C, 12 gigabytes. If you got this right,
I am extremely impressed. Um, this was
easy to miss and is also something that
is uh that is really really increasingly
important as we're starting to get
smaller models available for inference.
Um,
so with that, um, thank you so much for
attending today. Um, for learning, for
the great questions that you've been
asking on Discord. We're excited to see
you come back tomorrow. Um, and make
sure that you tally up your answers for
the pop quizzes, um, so you can see how
you um how you've been improving over
time. Um, really hope you enjoyed
learning more about foundational models
and prompt engineering. And tomorrow we
will see you back bright and early for
vector databases and embeddings. Um,
till next time, uh and thank you again.